Guide to the South Texas Jewish Archives vertical file, 1912-2023 MS 772
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
South Texas Jewish Archives vertical file
1912-2023
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Furman, Joshua, Dr.
MS 772
6 Linear Feet 1 file drawer, 2 boxes, 1 map-drawer
The collection includes individual files within the South Texas Jewish Archives including materials including: newsclippings, notes, correspondence, photographs, and other materials. The contents are donated by community members and/or gathered by the HJHA staff.
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 2017 in the wake of Hurricane Harvey, as the Houston Jewish History Archive, the name was changed in January 2023 to the Joan and Standford Alexander South Texas Jewish Archives (STJA). STJA is dedicated to the study and preservation of Jewish life in South Texas. By collecting artifacts from all facets of Jewish life, the STJA sheds light on how Jews in and around Houston have balanced maintaining their traditions and heritage with adapting to life in Texas and the United States.
For more information related to HJHA visit their website: https://jewishstudies.rice.edu/houston-jewish-history-archive
Scope and Contents
The collection includes individual files from the South Texas Jewish Archives including: newsclippings, notes, correspondence, photographs, and other materials. The contents are donated by community members and/or gathered by the HJHA staff.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged alphabetically in one series as follows:
Series I: STJA People, Places, and Events
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were acquired by a variety of individuals and organizations starting in 2018.
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
personal correspondence; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Records (documents); books; photographs; directories; Programs (Publications); Informational works; Collectibles
Subjects (Persons)
Furman, Joshua, Dr.
Subjects (Corporations)
Congregation Adath Yeshurun (Houston, Tex.); Congregation Adath Emeth (Houston, Tex.); Congregation Emanu El (Houston, Tex.); Congregation Shearith Israel (Wharton, Tex); United Orthodox Synagogues of Houston (Houston, Tex.)
- Series I: STJA people, places, events
  - 1900 Galveston storm aftermath memoir, 1900-09-08; Kaplan, Jay
    Kaplan, Jay
  - "A Service of Prayer and Dedication," World War II Interfaith Prayer Service in Houston, 1942-02-01; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
    Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - "A Handbook of True Facts Concerning the 'Basic Principles' of Congregation Beth Israel", 1944
  - AP photograph of Marvin Zindler, Harris County Sheriff's Office, 1972-01
  - Alfred's of Houston Delicatessen menu, ca. 1948-1990s; Jucker, Bobby; 1 Files 1 map-drawer
    Jucker, Bobby
  - Alfred's Deli menu with daily specials insert, 1966-01-04; Furman, Joshua, Dr. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alfred's matchbook, n.d.; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - American Associates, Ben Gurion University of the Negev, Greater Texas Region event materials, 2020; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - BBG pin - Star of Deborah belonging to Bonnie Goldberg, 1981-1983; Winograd, Bonnie G. (Box 2, Envelope 9)
    Winograd, Bonnie G.
  - BBYO Lonstar Region #73 27th Annual Regional Convention booklet, 2011-12-20-2011-12-23
  - BBYO District 7 group photo - Centenary College in Shreveport, Louisiana, c. 1960s
  - BBYO embroidered shirt, 1965; Jasuta, Stephanie Sherbel (Box 2, Envelope 3)
    Jasuta, Stephanie Sherbel
  - BBYO Texoma Regional Directory, 1961
  - B.H.B. Club (Adath Yeshurun) dance programs (3), 1935-1939; Robinson, Ileene
    Related Materials
    Katz Family Papers, MS 872, contains a photograph from the 1939 B.H.B. Club dance.
  - Bat Mitzvah kippah belonging to Mia Rani Rubenstein, 2022-04-09 (Box 2, Envelope 7)
  - Bat Mitzvah recording, Marilynne Altschuler and Stephanie Margulis, and Emanu El Sabbath Service Eve program, 1971-01-22-1971-01-23 (Box 1, Envelope 11)
  - Battelstein's service pins (3), n.d.; Furman, Joshua, Dr. (Box 2)
  - Bellaire High School class ring belonging to Lynn Ray Rosenthal Goldberg, 1961; Winograd, Bonnie G. (Box 2, Envelope 8)
  - Ben T. "Buddy" Lewis WWII Memoir and information files, c. 1940s-2005; Klein, Lisa
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Lisa Klein donated the materials on May 14, 2018.
    Ben T. Lewish's name appears on the Beth Jacob banner (MS 712).
    World War (1939-1945); Klein, Lisa
  - Beth Ha-Yeled graduation photograph, 1956; Krakower, Jay
  - B'nai B'rith Women Charter Certificate for Tikvah Chapter #1664, 1979-12-18; Wagman, Rose Marie (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Wagman, Rose Marie
  - Booklet: "Israel - The First 25 Years," distributed by the Jewish Community Council of Metropolitan Houston, 1973; Weidman, Judy
  - Booklet / Play by Meyer Leving titled Anne Frank, adapted from The Diary of Anne Frank from Beth Am Library, n.d.; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Brochure, The Shaarith Israel synagogue, Dallas, 1919
  - Camp Young Judaea - Kerrville, TX, group photograph, 1959; Taksa, Mari (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Taksa, Mari
  - Camp Young Judaea - Wimberley, Texas sticker, 1973
  - Camp Young Judaea Texas Address Book, Summer 2000
  - Cantor George Wagner recording, "Anniversary Waltz" and "Besame Mucho" [LP] (oversize), c. 1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Centennial Journal of Mount Sinai Congregation [Texarkana, TX], 1985; Estes, Gideon, Rabbi
    Estes, Gideon, Rabbi
  - Certificate of Resolution, Congregation Adath Yeshurun (facsimile), 1947; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Confirmation class photo, Congregation Beth Israel, 1935; Elbaz, Carol Ritter
    Elbaz, Carol Ritter
  - Confirmation class photo, Beth Jacob (Houston), 1944; Gerson, Rae
  - Confirmation program, Congregation Beth El, 1927; Hart, Charles
    Hart, Charles
  - Congregation Adath Emeth, Certificate of Appreciation given to Hyman Danziger, 1956-09-27
  - Congregation Adath Yeshurun confirmation and graduation program, 1938-06-05
  - Congregation Adath Yeshurun Sunday School group photograph (4), 1940; Gold, Roxanne Rosenberg
    Gold, Roxanne Rosenberg
  - Congregation Agudas Achim - San Antonio, Diamond Anniversary book, 1964; Hager, Roslyn
    Hager, Roslyn
  - Congregation Beth El Anniversary Gala programs (2), 2012-2017; Silver, Jay
    Silver, Jay
  - Congregation Beth El history, 1994; Silver, Jay
  - Congregation Beth Israel fundraising letter, 1950; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Congregation Beth Yeshurun Certificate of Merit for Louis Rosenberg, 1948-02-13; Gold, Roxanne Rosenberg
  - Congregation Beth Yeshurun confirmation photograph, c. 1950; Gold, Roxanne Rosenberg
  - Congregation Beth Yeshurun Confirmation program, 1956-05; Goodfriend, Carol F.
    Goodfriend, Carol F.
  - Congregation Beth Yeshurun Day School graduation booklet, 1959; Krakower, Jay
  - Congregation Beth Yeshurun Museum Minyan Memories, 25th Anniversary booklet, 2022; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Congregation Beth Yeshurn program, 2019-09-20
  - Congregation B'nai Zion's Anniversary Celebration program, 2022
  - Congregation Emanu El booklet, ca. 1960
    Scope and Contents
    Includes brochure on Communism, "An Affirmative Answer to Communism," written by Rabbi Kahn.
    Congregation Emmanu El, MS 726
  - Congregation Emanu El confirmation photograph, 1949; Stein, Paula Schwartz
    Stein, Paula Schwartz
  - Congregation Rodfei Sholom (San Antonio), fundraising brochure, 1989; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Consecration service photograph, Congregation Beth El, 1943-10; Lipper, Myra
    Lipper, Myra
  - Correspondence between David Safadi and the board of UOS regarding ritual practice, 1980-08
  - Daniel Bissonnet photographs (Roberta Harris and Congregation Beth Am)
  - Draft, "I Remember When", 1983; Spector, Emily; Cohen, Mirl
    One typed draft of the book, "I Remember When," which is an anthology of essays written by residents of Seven Acres senior center as part of an essay writing contest. The volume was compiled by Emily Spector who was the chairperson of the Essay Committee.
    Cohen, Mirl
  - E.H. Littman papers, Wharton Country Club - bylaws and correspondence, 1949-1955; Littman, John; Littman, Edward H.
    Material donated by John Littman in September 2018.
    Antisemitism; Littman, John; Congregation Shearith Israel (Wharton, Tex)
  - Event materials from "In Celebration of the Unveiling of 'Spring'" by Chaim Goldberg, 1980
    Biographical / Historical
    Chaim Goldberg was born in Kazimierz, Poland in 1917. He began to sculpt at the age of five and to paint when he was six. He was discovered at the age of 14 and taken under the patronship of several wealthy sponsors. He was admitted to the Academy of Fine Arts in Warsaw at the age of 17. He had a studio in Houston for a time where he created large format sculpture, paintings, and graphics in various media. He died in Florida in 2004.
    Programs (Publications)
  - Event materials from The Musical Legacy of Cantor Meir Finkelstein, 2022; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Football game program, Ball High School (Galveston) vs. San Jacinto High School, 1950-09; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - "From Generation to Generation," Congregation Beth Israel 125th Anniversary booklet, 1979
  - Graduation photo, Independent Hebrew School of Houston, ca. 1952; Schultz, Leah
    Schultz, Leah
  - Hadassah Magazine article, "The Jewish Traveler: Houston", 2014-10-2014-11; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Hebrew Academy class photos, 1987-1992
  - Hebrew Free Loan Association, 1932-2020; Bamberger, Terri
    Bamberger, Terri
  - Hirsch Brothers letter with envelope, 1937-12-18; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - "History of Emanu El's Beginnings" and Personal History/Biography, by Robert I. Kahn, 1983; Lipper, Myra
  - Houston Jewish businesses matchbooks, n.d.
  - Houston Pecan Company profile, Houston Chronicle, 2007-11; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Invitation to Congregation Beth Israel's Bible Festivals Home Tour, 1965-02
  - Invitation to Congregation K'nesseth Israel (Baytown) 90th Anniversary Celebration, 2019-04
  - Invitation to JCC grand opening, 2023-02-26
  - Isidore Katz of Waxahachie, Texas - deportation case documentation, 1937-1938; Katz, Lawrence
  - JCC Connect Magazine, Winter/Spring issue, 2016-12; Stolar, Leah
    Stolar, Leah
  - JCC Maccabi Games pins, 2003-2008
  - JCC Senior Olympics pin, n.d.
  - JCC - Houston t-shirt commemorating the Independence Day Run, 1981-05-10; Furman, Joshua, Dr. (Box 2)
  - JWB National Basketball Tournament program, Jewish Community Center, Houston, 1977-04; Lewis, Michael
    Lewis, Michael
  - Jean Rosenbaum, "This I Remember: A Memoir," Jewish Life in Galveston and Baytown TX, 2020; Rosenbaum, Jean
  - Jewish Family Service Houston Leadership event materias, Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Jewish Herald Voice magazine - Party Planners, 2020-2022; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Jewish Herald Voice magazines (4), 100th,110th, 114th, 115th Anniversary Passover editions, 2008; 2018, 2022; 2023; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Jewish Herald Voice magazine - Ninetieth Anniversary Passover Edition, 1998-04-11; Furman, Joshua, Dr. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jewish Herald Voice magazine - 112th Anniversary Passover Edition, 2020-04-09; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Jewish Herald Voice magazine - Rosh Hashanah Edition, 2019-2022; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Jewish Herald Voice "Voices" magazine, 2020-2021; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Jewish organizations' face masks, 2020-2021 (Box 2, Envelope 2)
  - The Jews in Houston and Galveston, Texas, During the Civil War, 1963; Ratkin, Gary A.
  - Johnson Junior High speech banquet program, 1970-1971; Wisenberg, S.L.
  - Josh Wolf, Bowman Draft superfractor rookie card, 2019; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Judith Weidman citizenship course certificate and JCC natrualization ceremony program, 1984-1985; Weidman, Judy
  - Junior Hadassah dance program, 1936-05; Robinson, Ileene
    Program donated by Ileene Robinson via Arlene Staller
  - Kinky Friedman for Governor posters (2), 2006; 2010; Furman, Joshua, Dr. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Kippah from Josh Furman's Bar Mitzvah, Congregation Rodfei Sholom, 1994-05-28 (Box 2, Envelope 1)
  - Leon and Jonas Levy, certificate of donation to the Jewish Consumptives' Relief Society, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Linda Lait Burger JCC and BBYO materials, 1978-1982; Burger, Linda L.
  - "Lucy Linda Sweet Peas" can label, Weingarten's
  - Margaret Jelinek Lewis family papers, 1991; Lewis, Margaret Jelinek
    One folder containing a skullcap, correspondence, and an invitation document a bar mitzvah held at the Rice University Chapel in 1991.
    Lewis, Margaret Jelinek
  - Marvin Zindler Deputy Sheriff business card
  - Maxim's Restaurant Francais menu, n.d.; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Menus (2), Kenny & Ziggy's Delicatessen Restaurant (in house and catering), Furman, Joshua, Dr. (Map-drawer 189, Folder 14)
  - Meyer Goldberg BBYO photographs (7) (oversize), c. 1960s - c. 1970s; Goldberg, Meyer (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Goldberg, Meyer
  - Meyerland Plaza development t-shirt, Katz, M. Marvin (Box 2)
    General
    Ed Wolfe gave this shirt to Marvin Katz, who represented Ed in negotiations to purchase the mall for redevelopment.
    Katz, M. Marvin
  - Minutes of the Golden Age Friendship Club, Jewish Community Center, 1975-1977; Hiller, April S.
    Material donated by April S. Hill in January 2019.
    Hiller, April S.
  - National Council of Jewish Women booklet - Celebrates the Bat Mitzvah Year of the Intergenerational Women's Seder, 2006-04-06; Stolar, Leah
  - Morris Heifetz video interviews, n.d.; Heifetz, Aaron
    Heifetz, Aaron
  - Newsletter of the Texas Jewish Historical Society, Vol. 1, No. 1, 1980-08
  - Norddeutscher Lloyd SS Bremen booklet (contains passenger lists and sailing schedule to Galveston and elsewhere), 1908; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Oral history interview with Max Schmidt of New Braunfels, 1973-09
  - Passover letter from soldier, Albert Greenhouse, Camp Wolters, Texas, 1943-04-21
    This file contains a letter from Greenhouse thanking the ladies from his congregation back home for a care-package he received while stationed at Camp Wolters.
    personal correspondence
  - Photograph, taken at Colt 45s baseball stadium (Rick Treiman, Barry Bisman, Larry Busman, and Bruce Schimmel), 1964; Schimmel, Sandra
    Schimmel, Sandra
  - Photograph, Conclave of Rabbis, Tyler, Texas, 1964; Sherman, Ruth G.
  - Photograph of house (possibly Sylvia Farb's childhood home), n.d.; Croft, Paul
  - Photograph, groundbreaking of Craig's Department Store, Wulfe, Lori
    The photo was taken at the construction site for Craig's Department store in Rice Village located at 2501 Univerisity Blvd. Persons in the photo from L to R are: Robert Grossman, Charles Grossman, Nancy Frimer Landa, and Gary Grossman (all children of the owners of Craig's).
    Wulfe, Lori
  - Photographs (10) Jerome Sherman and Beth Israel High School students at TOFTY weekend, Camp Carol, Ft. Worth, 1963; Sherman, Ruth G.; 1 Files 1 folder
  - Photographs and genealogy materials for Sam Zeisman and Jenny Victor (both on the Beth Jacob WWII banner), ca. 1945-2018; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Photograph of Jerry Hitt, signed to Carnell's Coffee Shop, n.d.
  - Photographs, members of Jewish Federation of Greater Houston and Jewish Community Center, ca. 1940s - ca. 1960s; Mann, Goldie
    Photographs of J.B. Lightman, Adele Heymann, Francis Schlosser, and Elizabeth Moser
    Mann, Goldie
  - Photographs, Rabbi Jack Segal photograph, Congregation Neveh Zedek, Portland, 1957-1960
  - Photograph, Rabbi Samuel Stahl, D.H.L. at Temple Bethel Chapel, 1991; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Photograph, University of Texas Sigma Alpha Mu, 1960; Winograd, Bonnie G. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photograph taken at an intersection on Braeswood with signs for "Yom Limmud Entrance" and "Rodeo Parking", c. 2018; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Photograph, Texoma Regional Convention (oversize), 1963; Kantor, Carol (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Kantor, Carol
  - Postcard, antisemitic image, 1907; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Postcard, Jewish Home for the Aged (Houston), n.d.
  - Postcard photograph of Clara Baum Pransky, Galveston, 1917
  - Postcard, U.S. Life Saving Station and Federal Immigration Station, Galveson, Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Postcard, Synagogues of Texas
  - Proof of Coca-Cola bottle cap, certified Kosher for Passover by the Houston Rabbinical Association, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Program, "city-wide meeting: Protest Treatment of Soviet Jewry", 1969; Weidman, Judy
  - Program, Congregation Beth El (Fort Bend Co.) Silver Anniversary Celebration, 2007-05-19; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Program, Rabbi Jack Segal's funeral service, 2023-07-10; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Promotional poster, Fredell Lack (oversize), 1960-02; Furman, Joshua, Dr. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Stanford J. Alexander memorial service program and tributes in the Jewish Herald Voice, 2022-07-01
  - "Putting the Shul in Schulenberg: The History of the Tri-County Jewish Community," article from The Goldring/Waldenberg Institute of Southern Jewish Life, Summer 2011; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Rabbi Henry Cohen (Galveston) - banquet programs and news articles, 1933-1937
  - Rabbis of San Antonio photographs, 1951-1989
    Purchased by Josh Furman
  - Ramblers Club photographs (2), 1938-1939; Hassid, Marilyn Levitch (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Hassid, Marilyn Levitch
  - Readings from the Holy Scriptures for Jewish members of the Armed Forces of the U.S. belonging to PFC. Henry J. Halprin, 1942
    PFC. Henry J. Halprin's name is on the Beth Jacob banner (MS 712).
    books
  - ReelAbilities, Houston Film and Arts Festival programs, 2020-2021; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Rice University Chabad materials, 2020; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Robert M. Beren Academy 50th Anniversary Scholarship Gala, 2019-03; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
    Program booklet and commemorative grace after meals book
  - Robt. I. Cohen Department Store advertisement printing block
  - Sakowitz catalogs (5), 1980-1989; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Sakowitz charge card, n.d.; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - San Jacinto High School class night programs, 1940; 1942
  - San Jacinto High School commencement program, 1952; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - San Jacinto High School invitation and list of graduates, 1951; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Seating list, 15th Annual Brotherhood Dinner, Houston Chapter of the National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1964-03; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Seven Acres Jewish Geriatric Center, Emblem of Tribute to Leo Dittman (certificate), 1988
  - Shearith Israel High Holiday choir photograph, c. 1964; Wadler, Michael
    Congregation Shearith Israel (Wharton, Tex)
  - Souvenir Edition of Houston Fifty Years Ago - Houston Chronicle, 1929-05; Wulfe, Lori; 1 Files (Box 1, Folder 5)
    A bound copy of the Houston Chronicle's "History of Houston" from May 1929. The volume includes an article regarding H. Grossman.
  - Souvenir Journal, The Hebrew Academy, 1978-1979; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Space Torah - A Jewish Journey in Space stamps and flyer, 1996; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - State of Israel Bonds certificate to Earl Lefkowitz, Lefkowitz, Jackie (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Lefkowitz, Jackie
  - State of Israel Bonds Tribute to the Wharton Chapter of Hadassah, 1990
  - State of Israel National Tribute Dinner program, 1976-10-27; Brookner, Michelle
  - Susan Resnick Papers (Second Jewish Feminist Conference, Yom Limmud, "A Seder for the Soviet Jews"), c. 1986-1992; Resnick, Susan
    One folder containing materials from the Second Jewish Feminist Conference, Yom Limmud workshop, "A Seder for the Soviet Jews."
    Resnick, Susan
  - Two Texas license plates - OY VEY, 1985-03
  - The Tides and Pilots of Zionism by Jacob B. Werlin, Halperin, Liora
    Halperin, Liora
  - Toomin, David - Profile in Jewish Herald Voice, 2000-10
  - TORCH 13th Anniversary Gala Dinner brochure, 2011-11
  - Toy catalogs, Lack's and Kaplan's Ben Hur, 1959; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - "A Tribute to Spirit: The Beth Israel Experience," DVD, 1976; Block, Gay
    Conditions Governing Access
    This DVD was pulled, cataloged and is available at the Woodson Research Center
  - Undergraduate research paper titled Judaism at Rice, by Rachel Rustin, 2003; Henson, Rachel Rustin
  - Union Home Prayer Book with Emanu El Confirmation, 1951-1960; Barnes, Carlotta
    Barnes, Carlotta
  - United Orthodox Synagogue announcement of election meeting, 1975-12-05; Kammerman, Ron
    Kammerman, Ron
  - The University Jewish Voice (3 issues), 1976-1977; Lefkowitz, Jeff
  - Weingarten's Food Stores 18-wheeler (toy), n.d.; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - Weingarten Family Materials, 1912-1952
    Two photographs, a news clipping, and genealogy materials document a very small part of the Weingarten family's activities in the Houston Jewish community and the growth of Weingarten's grocery chain.
  - Weingarten's memorabilia - token and sewing kit
  - Welcome to Houston: A Handbook for New Americans fro the Former Soviet Union, Rozin, Sara (Box 2)
    Rozin, Sara
  - West Houston JCC Boy Scouts collage, 1989; Hertz, Susan (Map-drawer 189, Folder 14)
    Hertz, Susan
  - Wooden nickels from Jewish synagogues, organizations, and events, 1964-1984; Furman, Joshua, Dr.
  - World War I prayer book belonging to Dave Steinberg, 1917; Gerson, Rae
    David Steinberg was born in Russia in 1896 before immigrating to the United States. He was the donor's father.
  - Yiddish Vinkl t-shirt (Box 2)
  - Yom Limmud (Day of Jewish Learning) 2020 materials, Furman, Joshua, Dr.